<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some considerations of present use wherein is shewn that the strong ought to bear with the weak, and the weak not clamour against or censure the strong, in which the true notion of the strong and weak is stated / delivered in a farewell-sermon at St. George Buttolph-Lane, London, by Benjamin Hoffman ...</title>
            <author>Hoffman, Benjamin.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44095</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2347</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36002</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15586059</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15586059</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103973</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44095)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103973)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1150:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some considerations of present use wherein is shewn that the strong ought to bear with the weak, and the weak not clamour against or censure the strong, in which the true notion of the strong and weak is stated / delivered in a farewell-sermon at St. George Buttolph-Lane, London, by Benjamin Hoffman ...</title>
                  <author>Hoffman, Benjamin.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for F. Gardiner ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes [1] p. advertisement at end.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans XV, 5-7 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103973:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103973:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOME CONSIDERATIONS OF <hi>Preſent Uſe:</hi> Wherein is ſhewn That the Strong ought to Bear with the Weak, and the Weak not Clamour againſt or Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Strong: IN WHICH The true Notion of the Strong and Weak is Stated.</p>
            <p>Delivered in a Farewell-Sermon at St. <hi>George Buttolph-Lane, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Benjamin Hoffman,</hi> Maſter of Arts, of <hi>Baliol</hi> College, <hi>Oxford,</hi> and late Lecturer there.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Rom. 15.1.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>We therefore that are ſtrong ought to bear the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities of the weak.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Rom. 16.17, 18.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now I beſeech you Brethren mark them which cauſe Diviſions and Offences contrary to the doctrine which you have learned, and avoid them: For they that are ſuch ſerve not our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but their own belly, and by good words and fair ſpeeches deceive the hearts of the ſimple.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>F. Gardiner</hi> at the <hi>White-horſe</hi> in <hi>Ludgate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet,</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:103973:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103973:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE DANIEL EARL OF NOTTINGHAM, BARON of <hi>DAVENTRY,</hi> And one of the Lords of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Moſt Honourable Privy-Council.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HOW great a Stranger ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I may be to Your Lordſhip, I am not much
<pb facs="tcp:103973:3"/>at a loſs for an Apologie for the Boldneſs of devoting this mean Preſent to Your Honourable Name. The inexpreſſible Favours I had the Honour to receive from Your Noble Father, have juſtly entitled Your Lordſhip to the beſt of my Performances: 'Twas His generous Charity made me what I am; and what the Product of that may be, is and ſhall be a due Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to Your Lordſhip. His Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues Your Lordſhip inherits; and nothing can more fully compleat the utmoſt Aim of my Ambition, than an Opportunity of ſhewing my ſelf Grateful to Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips
<pb facs="tcp:103973:3"/>Father's Immortal Memory, and of manifeſting my ſelf (in what Circumſtance ſoever)</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Lordſhips Moſt Obedient Servant, <hi>B. Hoffman.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:103973:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103973:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Pariſhioners of St.</hi> George Buttolph-Lane, <hi>and St.</hi> Buttolph's Billingsgate.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is not unknown to moſt Perſons that have known me, what Relation for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral years laſt paſt I have ſtood in to you, and ſince we liv'd ſo friendly and kindly together for ſo long a time, I was reſolv'd to do all in me lay, to part as fairly at the laſt, and to leave ſome certain Teſtimony of my Reſpect behind me: And ſince it is at this time the Indeavour of divers Learned Men in the Church, to Sweeten and Reconcile Mens Minds to the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that ſo the Civil Power may not ſurprize them, without due warning, and weighty Reaſons given, why they ought now eſpecially to indeavour
<pb facs="tcp:103973:5"/>an Union: Since ſeveral others are upon this Charitable, and Seaſonable Deſign, I thought my Words might come among you with more Eſteem and Reception than a meer Stranger's: And though I every way fall ſhort of the worth of thoſe other Perſons, that have bended their Purpoſes this way, yet when I conſider the Kindneſſes I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd from moſt of you, in all other Caſes, I cannot in the leaſt imagine I ſhall be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed in my Expectations, now, in this laſt piece of Reſpect I am ſhewing to you; and if it doth (in the peruſal) any Perſon Service, I ſhall heartily thank God, and really Rejoice in my Brothers return.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am Your Faithful Servant, <hi>Benjamin Hoffman.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103973:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Rom. XV. 5, 6, 7.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now the God of patience and conſolation, grant you to be like minded one towards another, according to Chriſt Jeſus,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That you may with one mind and one mouth glorifie God, even the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wherefore receive ye one another, as Chriſt alſo received us, to the glory of God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I proceed to the diſtinct ſpeaking to the Words of my Text, it is neceſſary that I firſt lead you to the Conſideration of the Apoſtle's Method and Deſign in two or three of the foregoing Chapters.</p>
            <p>Now the ſum of that which the Apoſtle is arguing, is laid down in the 13th Chapter of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:103973:6"/>this Epiſtle: In the whole he is managing the Jewiſh and the Chriſtian Profeſſors, and ſuch as were partly of one, and partly of the other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, with all the caution and warineſs that can be poſſibly, that he may give none offence to either: And in order to this he lays down Rules that ought to be univerſally received by Men of all Pretenſions. And theſe he begins with in the 13th Chapter and firſt Verſe, <hi>Let every ſoul,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>be ſubject to the higher pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, for there is no power but of God;</hi> therefore let your leſſer Diſputes be of what nature they will, if you believe a God, you muſt be Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, <hi>for the powers that be are ordained of God;</hi> as if he had ſaid, Nothing in Chriſtianity ought to be pretended, or made uſe of, to give any man Immunity from Obedience; for this from all Subjects, of what Quality ſoever, is due to thoſe to whom Allegiance belongs. And this Doctrine he preſt in oppoſition to ſome that St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Jude</hi> reprehended, <hi>viz. Such as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe Government, and are ſelf-willed and preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous, and that are not afraid to ſpeak evil of Dignities,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10. And this Obedience he preſſes <hi>v.</hi> 5. that it muſt be <hi>from the heart:</hi> It's poſſible a cunning Rebel, or proſperous Often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:103973:6"/>may avoid Wrath and Puniſhment, and therefore his Obedience muſt not be for fear of Wrath only, <hi>i. e.</hi> not only ſo far as will keep him from a Fine, a Priſon, or a Gallows; but it muſt be <hi>from his Conſcience, i. e.</hi> in Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Conſtitution of God, whoſe Officer he is: For every Supreme Magiſtrate, Legally placed in any Kingdom, hath, and muſt be thought to have, Commiſſion from God, tho' he be an Heathen.</p>
            <p>And after the Apoſtle had managed this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument throughly, how Chriſtians ſhould car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry themſelves towards their Governours, he then deſcends to tell us how they ſhould carry themſelves one towards another; and for this he lays down Love and Charity, and Bearing one with another, as the Foundation and Ground-work of all good Chriſtian Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and here at the time of writing this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle he found great Diviſions and Diſſentions already crept into the Church of Jewiſh Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, not only againſt the Gentiles, but likewiſe among themſelves, ſome <hi>Converts</hi> clearly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerning that they had a freedom from the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daical Yoke, and others conceiving themſelves ſtill to be under that Diſpenſation; and hence
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103973:7"/>came the Quarrel, <hi>viz.</hi> That thoſe that were zealous for the Moſaical Law, condemned and were angry at all others, as Breakers of God's Law, that did not obſerve them as they did; and on the other hand, they that were inſtructed in the Knowledge of their <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> were reſolved to maintain that Liberty which was purchaſed by Chriſt, and were apt to deſpiſe and contemn thoſe that ſtill continued ſcrupulous in the aboliſht Judaical Rites, and ſo between the one and the other, the Chriſtian Communion was likely to be broken, and an inveterate Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration to be made among them; and to both of theſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> applies himſelf, Thoſe of you that do not think your ſelves bound to obſerve thoſe Laws, you that underſtand better, do not you reject the ſcrupulous or erroneous Judai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer, but receive him to your Communion; <hi>Him that is weak in the Faith receive ye,</hi> but yet ſo receive him, as that he may not thereby be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to take too much upon him; <hi>receive him, but not to doubtful diſputations;</hi> as if he had ſaid, If he be weak and erroneous in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, let him not be cenſorious and troubleſome to others; do not you deſpiſe and reject him, neither perſwade I that he ſhould moleſt you;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103973:7"/>ſo that this Chapter was writ, and this Advice here given, that the ſtrong might be gentle and courteous towards the weak, and not the weak from hence be clamorous againſt the ſtrong, as ſome (eſpecially in theſe days) make this and ſuch like advice in Holy Writ, to be as it were a Shelter and a Sanctuary for them to do and ſay what they pleaſe, under the pretence of Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and that prudent and legal Reſtraints muſt not be talkt of, without grieving or judging our Brother. But there is a great deal of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between mildly and wiſely indeavouring to reduce men to <hi>Catholick Communion,</hi> and between offering any Offence, or Deſpiſing them, as I ſhall ſhew farther anon; and St. <hi>Paul</hi> plainly doth it in the following Chapter; for if, ſaith he, after ſo much Charity and Tenderneſs and Good-will that the ſtrong bear towards the weak, they do not hearken, then the Offence lies on their ſide, and at their doors and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17, 18. <hi>Now I beſeech you Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren mark them which cauſe diviſions and offences,</hi> and if after all the friendly Offers you make to Communion, they will not comply, <hi>avoid them, for they which are ſuch ſerve not our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but their own belly and intereſt, and by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103973:8"/>good words and fair ſpeeches deceive the hearts of the ſimple.</hi> And thus for the introducing my enſuing Diſcourſe, I have ſhewed you the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the Apoſtle; which is as I ſhew'd you,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To lay down hearty Obedience to Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, as the indiſpenſible Duty of all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and Men that own a God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To have Chriſtians friendly towards each other, the ſtrong not to Deſpiſe or Scorn the weak, and the weak not to Clamour at and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the ſtrong; that the ſtrong ſhould more value his Brother's Soul, than a needleſs hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouring and pleaſing himſelf, <hi>ch.</hi> 15. <hi>v.</hi> 1. and that the weak ſhould not be Loud and Poſitive in Diſputations that he doth not underſtand: And that all in their ſeveral places may do this, he propoſeth both the Fountain and Example of all Heavenly and Chriſtian Graces, <hi>Now the God of patience and conſolation grant you to be like minded one towards another, according to Chriſt Jeſus, wherefore receive ye one another, as Chriſt alſo received us, to the glory of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon theſe Words I ſhall briefly and plainly diſcourſe upon theſe following things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Give a ſhort and eaſie Explication of the Words of the Text.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:103973:8"/>
            <p n="2">2. In ſome few Words touch upon the Duty of Obedience to Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I ſhall principally endeavour to ſhew you how we ought to carry our ſelves towards each other with reference to Communion, the Strong to the Weak, and the Weak to the Strong; which may ſerve as a Method or Incitement to us to be <hi>like-minded one towards another,</hi> that we may <hi>with one mind and one mouth gloriſie God,</hi> and <hi>receive one another as Chriſt alſo received us, to the glory of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Conclude with ſome Practical Reflexions upon the Whole.</p>
            <p>As for the Text, the Apoſtle is here wiſhing a very great Bleſſing upon the Infant Chriſtian-Church; and he founds the Riſe of all Bleſſings in God: And ſo the meaning of the Words is this; Now (ſaith he) I have laid down as amply and as plainly as I can the Duty of Chriſtians one towards another, I beſeech God, who is the Fountain of Patience and Conſolation, <hi>the God of Patience and Conſolation, i. e.</hi> the God from whom all Patience and Conſolation comes, <hi>make you to be like minded one towards another, i. e.</hi> cauſe that you may all think and own the very ſelf-ſame thing, leſt through diverſity of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103973:9"/>Opinions, there ariſe Diſcords, Hatreds, Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Offences, and Scandals, to the great da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the Church and Glory of God: Or if there be ſome little difference in Opinion among you, don't ſeparate, and break aſunder, and rend the Communion of the Church of Chriſt; yet ſtill <hi>be like minded one towards another, i. e.</hi> come with equal degrees of Charity and Love one towards another, and hope the beſt one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for that the ſenſe no doubt is, that by <hi>like-mindedneſs</hi> is meant agreeing in the ſame Truths, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to think the very ſame thing. So that the plain meaning no doubt is this; God grant, ſaith the Apoſtle, that your Heats and Differences being laid aſide, whether about the Obſervation of Meats, or Days, or the like, that you may think and agree mutually in the ſame thing, and that <hi>according to Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> This is added, to reſtrain them from agreeing in any falſe or erroneous Opinions; but wiſhes their ſenſe of Religion to be agreeable to Chriſt, the Author of all Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That you may with one mind and one mouth glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God:</hi> That when you come to pray to, or praiſe God, you may not onely do it in the ſame Form and ſound of Words, but alſo with all
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103973:9"/>your Minds full of mutual Affection one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another, without any ſurly demeanour, contempt, hatred, or cenſuring of each other, that you may do it ſo unanimouſly, as if there were but one Mind and one Mouth among you. He would have the Weak and the Strong lay aſide their Differences, and joyn in the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals, to <hi>gloriſie God</hi> together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>receive ye one another, as Chriſt alſo received us, to the glory of God: i. e.</hi> Look upon each other as Brethren; in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility of kindneſs and condeſcenſion, embrace and ſuccour one another: In ſtead of deſpiſing and driving Men from your Communion, help up them that are fallen, let one endeavour to bring the other to himſelf, the Strong reduce the Weak, the Learned the Ignorant, and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Gentile, the prejudiced Jew: and let him cheriſh, and inſtruct, and be tender of him, with a Brotherly Care and Affection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Even as Chriſt alſo received us, to the glory of God.</hi> Chriſt did much more than all this for us, that he adviſeth us to do one for another. Chriſt did not diſdain us, that are more unworthy of his Preſence, than we are of each others. So our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſaith by <hi>St. John,</hi> ch. 17. v. 24. <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103973:10"/>I will that thoſe whom thou haſt given me, be with me where I am, that they may behold my glory which thou haſt given me.</hi> So that Chriſt recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us into the Fellowſhip and Partnerſhip of the Glory of God, and therefore we ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive one another.</p>
            <p>So that the whole meaning of the Text is, The Apoſtle beſeeches God to grant them the ſame Sentiments and Underſtanding of the true Religion of Chriſt; or if they have not juſt the very ſame Sentiments of things in every Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, (as it may be few Men have) yet that they would not rend and tear Chriſt's Church, but would lay aſide their diſlikes of each others pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Opinion, and with one Heart and one Mouth joyn together in Publick Duties and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and receive one another in the viſible Communion of the Chriſtian Church: that the Weak ſhould not as Malecontents go to ſeparate themſelves, and throw away their Souls; nor the Strong (as having a clearer Underſtanding) diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain to joyn with the Weak; but that we ſhould <hi>receive one another,</hi> to the helping each other for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in Grace, as Chriſt alſo offers to receive us to the Eternal Being with him in Glory. And now having ſpoke diſtinctly to the Words of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103973:10"/>Text, I ſhall paſs to the ſecond thing, which I ſhall inſiſt on very briefly. And that is,</p>
            <p n="2">2. To conſider that great Duty of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Magiſtrates. And this I ſhould not have mentioned now, but onely that <hi>St. Paul</hi> lays it down as the firſt ſtep to Peace and Order in the Chriſtian Church; and likewiſe becauſe the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute of Days and Meats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is out of doors between us and our Brethren the Diſſenters, and becauſe they ſeem as much blunder'd and puz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led about the extent of Obedience to our Laws, as the Jews were of theirs; which is the reaſon why I touch upon this <hi>Duty</hi> as I go. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed their being ſo much miſtaken in the extent of Chriſtian Obedience, is that (I fear) which makes them take ſo little notice of the Laws of a Reformed Chriſtian Prince: for if the Power of a Heathen Prince be from God, and that <hi>he that reſiſts</hi> him, <hi>ſhall receive damnation to himſelf;</hi> much more, when <hi>one</hi> (as I may ſay) <hi>after God's own heart</hi> is in the Throne, when he counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances that ſame Religion which we pretend to love at our very Hearts, and which our Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers ſealed with their Blood.</p>
            <p>Theſe Conſiderations (methinks) might make us run Voluntiers in Obedience to him, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103973:11"/>cauſe us to ſtifle all the <hi>little Tricks and Humours</hi> of our own, when God and the King go thus together in our <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Nay, beſides all this, our Laws are not the Breath of one ſingle Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon only, but proceed from the mature Delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Men of our own chuſing, to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent our Grievances, and take care that no hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vier Burdens be laid on our Bodies, or Minds, than themſelves, as Fellow-ſubjects, are ready to bear. And yet ſtrange it is, that after all theſe wonderful Priviledges, we ſhould have ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pining at, and others defying our admirable Form and Methods of Government; that they ſhould allow none to be Lords over them; and that the Pretence of Chriſtian Liberty, ſhould fight and ſet it ſelf againſt the Laws of God and Man: and this we ſee by too ſad and daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience it doth. Whereas were our Prince in his Judgment a Heathen, in his Power furniſh'd to be arbitrarily and uncontrolably Cruel, and in his Will and Inclinations delighting to cruſh and grieve his Subjects; yet to this Power we muſt be obedient. In ſhort, be the Prince what he will, God requires a thorow Obedience one way or other; and therefore the thoughts of a Gracious, a Merciful, and a Reformed Prince,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:103973:11"/>ſhould make us ſo proud of, and pleas'd with our Governour, as not to thwart him upon Straws and Trifles. No Maſter, tho never ſo mean, but expects Dutifulneſs from his Servant: No Father, tho never ſo poor, but requires Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience from his Child. And why ſhould a Prince (who is above us all) ſuffer himſelf to be mock'd, when no body elſe will? Why ſhould he be called a Law-maker of his Country, if every humourous fanciful Perſon may control his Authority when he pleaſeth? This ſeems a great Affront to the Supreme Power on Earth, eſpecially a Power ſo great as to be <hi>ordained of God:</hi> Tho I really fear many Chriſtians do not know what they do, when, to the indulging ſome Humours of their own, they bid Adieu to all Authority, and do what in ſingle Perſons lies to the dividing Chriſtians, and confounding Church-Order and Diſcipline. But I hope bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of you, my Brethren; and therefore I ſhall not inſiſt any more upon this Head, only ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that of the Apoſtle, That <hi>you muſt be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, not only for wrath, but conſcience ſake, i. e.</hi> You muſt make Obedience to Governors as ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely your Deſire and Endeavour, as any other Goſpel-duty whatſoever. But I deſign'd only
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103973:12"/>to touch upon this Head; and therefore ſhall paſs to the next Head; and that is,</p>
            <p n="3">3. How Chriſtians ſhould carry themſelves towards each other with reference to Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, <hi>viz.</hi> the Strong to the Weak, and the Weak to the Strong, that ſo we may be <hi>like minded one towards another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Strong are thoſe that have an exact Knowledge of Things both Lawful and Unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and which think nothing that is Lawful to be Unlawful.</p>
            <p>The Weak are thoſe that think one or more Things that are Lawful, to be Unlawful: and their Weakneſs conſiſts in their doubting and miſtaking Judgments about Things that are Lawful.</p>
            <p>The Strong in the Apoſtles days were thoſe that thorowly underſtood what Liberty they had by Chriſt from the Jewiſh Ceremonies.</p>
            <p>The Weak in thoſe days were thoſe that thought well of Chriſtianity, and yet for all that were unwilling quite to throw off the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial Law, that ſtood upon <hi>Meats and Days, &amp;c.</hi> tho the Goſpel acquitted them.</p>
            <p>The Strong in our days are thoſe that are heartily obedient to all the Laws of Magiſtrates,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103973:12"/>that are not forbidden in Gods Word; and that are ſatisfied that a Prince hath Power to enjoyn any thing in our Worſhip, that is not excepted againſt in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>The Weak in our days are thoſe that either can't or won't diſtinguiſh between Articles of Faith, and Modes of Worſhip; that think they are not obliged, nay, that they ought not to obey their Governours, as to the enjoyning In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Things in their Worſhip, becauſe they are not commanded in Words at length in the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now having named to you the Men and the Thing, I ſhall proceed humbly to offer ſome Rules to your Conſideration, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p>And in theſe I ſhall apply my ſelf to the Strong and the Weak; and becauſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> in this Chapter begins with the Strong, I ſhall do ſo too. <hi>We therefore that are ſtrong ought to bear the infirmities of the weak,</hi> eſpecially if the Weak are as they were in thoſe days, (and perhaps had ſome reaſon to be) in a great ſtrait which to take; for it was doubtleſs very hard for Men then, eſpecially thoſe that were Zealous, to throw off a Religion almoſt wholly, and run with immediate ſatisfaction into another. It
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103973:13"/>was doubtleſs a great Surpriſe to them, that after a Religion had flouriſh'd about Four thouſand years, and had been owned by God as the True in all Ages before: I ſay, 'twould make any Man at a ſtand, to ſee one Perſon come and tell us of a ſudden, That <hi>neither Circumciſion nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſion availed any thing;</hi> that <hi>Meats and Days were all alike;</hi> and that <hi>the Old allowed and eſtabliſhed Law, muſt give way to a New Goſpel.</hi> I queſtion, if any of us had lived in thoſe days, and been bred up in the ſtricteſt Knowledge of the Law, how many of us would inſtantly have turned Chriſtians; eſpecially ſince ſo many of us now ſtumble, and are miſtaken about the Goſpel, tho the World hath been ſo long inur'd and accuſtomed to its Doctrine: ſo that there was great reaſon in thoſe days for the Strong to bear with the Weak, becauſe the Difficulties of rightly judging and diſcerning Things were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrong and maſculine, enough to throw down weak Minds But when <hi>Weakneſs</hi> is pretended, to make way for <hi>Confuſion;</hi> when Men will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend they are <hi>weak at one time,</hi> and will take it amiſs when you go to inſtruct them <hi>as ſuch at another;</hi> this looks rather like <hi>Wilfulneſs,</hi> than the <hi>Weakneſs</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> here means.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:103973:13"/>
            <p>But I am very well aware, that there is a very popular and current Obſervation in our days, which ſeems a great Objection againſt what I have hitherto ſaid; and that is, <hi>That Men can no more be ſuppoſed to be alike in Judgment, than they are in Features.</hi> But the Caſe is not at all the ſame. Men would, no doubt, be all exactly Featured alike, if God had deſign'd they ſhould be ſo, and had drawn them all as Copies from the ſame Original: But he hath given us all the very ſelf-ſame Law and Rule; he hath given us the ſame Faculties to judge with; and therefore it might juſtly be expected we ſhould all think the ſame things. One Soul hath no unlikeneſs to another, but onely from the different Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and Sentiments it receives: And if the Rules be all the ſame to manage our Souls by, whence comes the Unlikeneſs? Not from the neceſſary impreſt Features of the Soul, but from the wrong Apprehenſion and Management of the Rule. So that 'tis no fault not to be alike in outward Features, becauſe God never deſigned us all the ſelf-ſame external Aſpect: But 'tis a Crime not to <hi>think the ſelf-ſame truth, according to Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> becauſe this was the Reaſon of Gods giving us one unalterable Rule, <hi>that we
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103973:14"/>ſhould with one mind and one heart glorifie him.</hi> But I muſt paſs to the ſeveral Conſiderations, ſome to the Strong, and ſome to the Weak, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To the Strong, I deſire them to conſider theſe following Things, with reference to the Weak. By the Weak I mean thoſe that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſo, and not ſuch as uſe it for an obſtinate and ungovernable Pretence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I deſire the Strong to conſider, That their weak Brethren ſeem to have ſomewhat to ſay for themſelves. When I hear a Man telling me that he hath been educated in ſuch an Opinion, and his Parents before him, nay, and that he doth not owe his Opinion onely to the Font, but that he hath ſtrove, and prayed, and read, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, and conferr'd; that after all his Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, he cannot find that he hath any love for any Opinion, more than his unconquerable Perſwaſion fixes him: I ſay, when we hear a Man ſincerely, and from the bottom of his Heart, ſaying, That he cannot diſtinguiſh things as others can; that he cannot think that Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent which others do; that he cannot admit things that are really Lawful in others Opinion, to appear ſo in his: A Man that is Strong ought
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103973:14"/>to pity ſuch a ones Weakneſs: Tho, to my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, 'tis very ſtrange, if what theſe Men tell us, be true; 'tis very odd, that a Man out of the Church ſhall tell us, by his Eye-ſight, that a Houſe is a Houſe, a Tree a Tree, and a Man a Man, and ſee theſe things as clearly as any Man elſe; and yet have this Man into a Church, and you can't perſwade him, but that a plain whited Wall is a Carved or a Molten Image: For this is really the Caſe; Take theſe Men in Worldly Buſineſs, and they are as intelligent and as ſtrong and as rational as others: but in Religion they are as odd and aukerd and untractable: Tho, methinks, 'tis very ſad, that that Religion which Chriſt deſigned to enlighten, ſhould cloud and maze their Underſtandings: But yet thus we oft ſee it is, Men are thus either in pretence or reality weak; however that be, we muſt leave them to God, bear with their Weakneſs, and be glad to ſee them in our Communion. And if I can any thing judge of the Temper of thoſe that are of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I dare vouch for the wiſer and ſoberer part of them, that they do not diſdain Communion with the weakeſt Brother. But alas! the Caſe is now altered from that in <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s days; the VVeak refuſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:103973:15"/>Communion with the Strong, which ſeems to give a great contradiction to their pretended Weakneſs; for thoſe that really know them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves weak, would not throw themſelves out to the wide World, and pretend to take greater care for themſelves, than God in his Providence, and their Governours by their great Care offer to them. But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Strong ought to bear with and pity the Weak, in that they expoſe their Perſons and Fortunes to the Cenſure of the Magiſtrate, upon <hi>Needleſs things.</hi> Real Martyrdom, and laying down our Lives and Eſtates for the Truth, is highly commendable in the Eyes of God and Man: But to withſtand and contend with the Supreme Magiſtrate, when he is doing the true part of his Duty, is really a very great Evil; for a good Magiſtrate is the great Crown and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of a Nation; for by prudent Exerciſe of good and righteous Laws, he reduces many to a good and right Underſtanding of Things, that it may be would not elſe mind or conſider about Religion: And if the Magiſtrate doth not take care of his Subjects Souls, as well as their Bodies, he bears the beſt part of his Sword in vain; for People are very apt to run into
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103973:15"/>ſtrange Enthuſiaſms, when every Man may cut out what Religion he pleaſes; and we may well think a Prince blame-worthy in this Particular, if God own him as his Deputy and Vicegerent, and yet he doth nothing for God in all his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. And indeed we have all the reaſon in the World to give all due reſpect to the Laws (eſpecially) of Good Princes; for the higher the Office, the greater the Grace that deſcends upon them. But yet notwithſtanding the Prince, as a part of his Duty, takes care to ſee Religion ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercis'd; yet too many there are that dare to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, and expoſe their Lives and Fortunes to the dint of his Laws, and that for little, potty, trivial things: And theſe the Strong ought to pity; they ſeem to be in earneſt, when their Blindneſs will enable them to part with that which is dear to them, rather than obey. Therefore when we ſee any of our weak Brethren in trouble becauſe of their Weakneſs, let us not deride and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn them becauſe of their Weakneſs, but pity them, that they do not ſee tho Mercies of God; in ſo good a Prince, and ſuch good Laws. Let us not, I ſay, deſpiſe them; for, as the Apoſtle argues, <hi>Who made thee to differ?</hi> Was it not the Grade of God that reſcued thee from this Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:103973:16"/>And indeed the Sufferings even of a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Malefactor are pitiable, as we have a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Reſpect for Humane Nature. And this will induce our weak Brother to think that we are loving, and tender, and Chriſtian-like, when we do not mock at, but pity their Calamity. Tho 'tis very fit and meet that good and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Laws ſhould take place, and be executed upon Offenders; yet 'twould be hard, if thoſe that are to execute theſe Laws, or any other, ſhould ſuperadd any Cenſure, or intermingle any ſort of Treatment, that the Laws will not directly allow or do not expreſly enjoyn. 'Tis no Perſecution to put good and juſtifiable Laws in Execution; but it looks like one, when thoſe that are to do it, rejoyce in their Brothers Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings. But,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Strong ſhould conſider and pity the Meanneſs and Confuſion of their Faith and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. Now <hi>Faith,</hi> as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>comes by hearing;</hi> and therefore this Fault I ſhall rather chuſe to lay upon their Teachers, than upon them; tho 'tis in part their fault, to make no better a Choice. And I muſt confeſs, I take it to be the particular ſleight of their Preachers to cut out Work for themſelves, to make their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:103973:16"/>Hearers of nice and bogling Conſciences, that they may have them under their Dominion, to raiſe ſuch Scruples that they and none elſe care to anſwer, and render Religion an odd and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intelligible Undertaking. I muſt confeſs, I have not much heard their Sermons; but I have perus'd ſome of their Books, where a great deal of what they ſay is very formidable, and ſome again unintelligible Doctrine; where <hi>Nineteen</hi> Marks of Grace are ſet down, and ſtrictly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, when <hi>Two,</hi> or it may be <hi>never a one of them,</hi> will ſerve the turn. Now, for my part, I heartily pity any Hearer, that with Awe and Reverence puts his Soul into the Hands of a Teacher that is not Faithful, that drags him thorow a rough and tempeſtuous Way, when a much plainer and caſier is nigh at hand. Chriſt came to make Religion plain and eaſie; and if any Man that puzzles and entangles it, be his true Embaſſadour, judge ye. But having ſome Conſiderations to add to the other ſort of Men, the Weaker Brethren, I ſhall paſs to them, and ſpeak but briefly to them, and ſo conclude. And to theſe my Requeſt is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To have a competent and becoming Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence for Authority. And here I do not go
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:103973:17"/>perſwade theſe Men into the Notion of <hi>Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> as if all their Governours did or ſaid were as infallible as any part of the <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> but to deſire them to have in themſelves ductile, obedient, governable, and perſwaſive Frames of Spirit; not to be moroſe, or peeviſh, or ſowr, or obſtinate: And let the Conſideration of his being <hi>the Power and the Ordinance of God,</hi> carry them beyond all their little Doubtings and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections. <hi>A meek, and a quiet, and a ſubmiſſive Frame of Spirit, is in the ſight of God of great price.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. My Deſire to the Weak of our days is, ſeriouſly to conſider, That the Government can never provide againſt all the petty Exceptions of every particular Perſon; and that 'tis impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that all the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> can be pleas'd. Is not this to be prov'd within our Memory, when the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Independent</hi> (tho now they love ſo dearly) were as much Antichriſtian one to another, as now <hi>We</hi> are to Both? And if at this time the Government goes to comply with the Conſcience of the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> what then will become of the <hi>Independent?</hi> If the Mouths of both theſe can be ſtopp'd, what muſt be done for the <hi>Anabaptiſt?</hi> Or if theſe could be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:103973:17"/>complied with too, what ſhall we do for the great Numbers of <hi>Diſſenting Quakers?</hi> All theſe come in with a pretended equal Cry and Loud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Conſcience; and if theſe <hi>Dividers</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not condeſcend to each others Weakneſs, how can they expect the Government ſhould? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when they deſire that the Governours ſhould make ſuch Laws as ſhall ſuit every Mans Conſcience, that's impracticable, nay, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, without bringing abſolute Confuſion into the Church and State: Nay, themſelves, I dare ſay, do not deſire the Laws ſhould be made ſo looſe, as to take in all the ſeveral <hi>Sects</hi> of <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> and if it takes in one Party that is blinded and weakned by his Conſcience, why not another? If they object, <hi>That a little Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion would take in ſome:</hi> I beſeech them, On whoſe ſide ought the Condeſcenſion to lie? Is it not more feaſible that particular Perſons may come into the Church, than that the whole Form of Church and State-Government muſt be new-molded for them? If this be an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or modeſt Demand, I leave every Man (that can) to judge; and I think we may ſafely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake that the Government will grant, when all the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> are agreed what to ask, I mean,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:103973:18"/>that will make us <hi>all one, according to Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. My Deſire to the weak Brethren is, not to place Religion, or the Suſpenſion of it, in little trifling Indifferent Things. This was that our Saviour highly blamed in the <hi>Phariſees:</hi> Nay, is it not the extreme Dotage of ſome in our days, that think a Tag more the Goſpel-mode than a Ribband, or a ſhort Black Coat more Edifying and Evangelical, than a Gown or a Surplice? This is that which we really and truly call <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition</hi> in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that a Stick ſet on croſs ſhould be more Reverend and Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, than in any other Poſture. The Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and Truth of Religion lies in great and weighty Matters; and theſe (thanks be to God) our <hi>Diſſenters</hi> own we retain in the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> And therefore why do they fly us by reaſon of our Ceremonies? All that we ſay for them, is, That they are <hi>Ancient,</hi> and <hi>Decent;</hi> and who fitter to judge of <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Decency,</hi> than our Governours? If they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, <hi>Had theſe things been uſed in our Saviours time, they had not ſcrupled them:</hi> But how are we aſſured that they ſpeak truth in this Matter? The <hi>Sacraments</hi> were uſed in our Saviours time,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:103973:18"/>and yet a great number of our <hi>Diſſenters</hi> ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple them: The <hi>Creed</hi> was compiled in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time, and yet moſt of them boggle at ſome part of it, <hi>viz. The Communion of Saints,</hi> and the trueſt and moſt intelligible Notion of <hi>the Holy Catholick Church.</hi> Beſides, Chriſt and his Apoſtles had then neither Room, nor External Authority to plant and perfectly ſettle a Viſible Church; they could inſtil their Doctrines, and General Rules of Faith, but could not deſcend to all the Particular Modes of Worſhip: theſe we derive as faithfully as we can from the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians, which all ſober and wiſe Men have a great Veneration for. And indeed the Apoſtle hath given fair Power and Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Magiſtrates to be doing, when he bids them take care that <hi>all things be done decently and in order.</hi> And who is the beſt Judge of <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Decency,</hi> the Magiſtrate <hi>(the Ordinance of God)</hi> or the Weak Brother, I ſhall leave to Wiſe Men to determine. And whereas they oft object, <hi>That the Government muſt not enjoyn any thing but what is expreſly commanded in the Scriptures:</hi> If they will turn the ſame Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment fairly, it will amount to thus much direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt themſelves, <hi>viz.</hi> That they muſt not
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:103973:19"/>deny Obedience in any thing that is not poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and in plain Words forbidden; unleſs they think the Scripture allows them more Liberty than it allows the Magiſtrate, or that they ſhall have Liberty to diſobey in thoſe very Caſes, in which the Prince ſhall not have Power to enjoyn: And then let them ſhew us where the Scriptures deny a Surplice, or any other of our Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies retained and uſed. And do they deny Compliance becauſe of the Tenderneſs of their Conſcience? The Magiſtrate doth likewiſe, out of his tender Love and Care for the Church, and Uniformity in our Worſhip, enjoyn them; as well knowing, that ſome External Form of Church-Government is abſolutely needful; and none yet, after ſeveral Trials, can be pitch'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that are more decent, and leſs offenſive.</p>
            <p n="4">4. My laſt Deſire to weak Brethren is, that they would not throw themſelves out of the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Chriſts Catholick Church. By this they fruſtrate the Deſign of Chriſts coming into the World, and Dying for us. He came to make us all one: And, I perceive, they take it mightily in dudgeon to be Excommunicated; which (as they manage the Caſe) is onely a Publick Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what they themſelves have done long
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:103973:19"/>before. <hi>St. Paul</hi> doth not ſeem to imagine, that they would throw themſelves out of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; but was afraid that the Strong would not Communicate with them: And this we deſire with all our Souls to do; but, the miſchief of it is, our weaker Brethren think themſelves Holier and Wiſer, and, if ſo, much Stronger than we. And to theſe I may well uſe thoſe Words of the Wiſe-man, onely adviſable in ſuch Caſes as theſe, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.16. <hi>Be not righteous overmuch, neither make thy ſelf over wiſe; for why ſhouldeſt thou deſtroy thy ſelf?</hi> And why ſhould theſe Men, under a needleſs and unjuſtifiable Pretence of Sanctity, hazard their <hi>Souls,</hi> by rending the Communion of Chriſts Church, and by Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to Gods Governours? and their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and Eſtates, by undergoing the Penalty of our National Laws? <hi>Who hath required this at their Hands,</hi> that they ſhould ſet up for Martyrs, before they are called to bear witneſs to the Truth of Chriſt? And I wiſh to God theſe Men would ſeriouſly conſider, what 'tis to be out of the Communion of the Catholick Church. If there be but One Church, why do they not Communicate with us? why do they go out from us? If there be Two Catholick Churches,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:103973:20"/>what becomes of an entire Article of our <hi>Creed?</hi> Indeed there is no ſenſe in that Aſſertion. But I muſt not, I need not add any more to theſe Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. I hope what I have ſaid, will not be look'd upon either as ſharp, uncharitable, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable: What I have ſaid, is ſpoke out of a real deſire that you would be <hi>like minded one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another,</hi> that you would <hi>receive one another, as Chriſt alſo received us, to the Glory of God.</hi> I am well aware, that Men are not like Iron, to be hammer'd when they are heated, or to be hector'd and jeer'd into Communion and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; and therefore I have been all along plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the contrary: But I hope no Man will be angry, when we modeſtly and ſincerely tell him the Truth, as I have endeavoured plainly to do: Eſpecially, I would not leave any Diſtaſte with you, as to my Perſon or Temper, now in this laſt Exerciſe I am performing among you; for this would be ill Policy with reſpect to my Future Undertakings, and an ill Requital to that Kindneſs I own I have received from all Parties among you. I ſhall onely beg your Prayers and Well-wiſhes for my Future Undertakings, and Succeſs in my Performances, and conclude all with thoſe Words of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.11,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:103973:20"/>14. <hi>Finally, Brethren, farewell; be perfect, be of one mind, live in peace, and the God of love and peace ſhall be with you. The grace of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the love of God, and the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Holy Ghoſt, be with, bleſs, preſerve, and guide you, from this time forth for evermore.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:103973:21"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>FINCHAM GARDINER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Continuation and Vindication of the Defence of Dr. <hi>Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleets</hi> Unreaſonableneſs of Separation, in Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Lob,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>An Anſwer to the Diſſenters Objections againſt the Common Prayers, and ſome other Parts of Divine Service Preſcribed in the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Caſe of Kneeling at the holy Sacrament Stated and Reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Wherein theſe Queries are conſidered, 1. Whether Knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at the Sacrament be contrary to any expreſs Command of Chriſt, obliging to the obſervance of a different Geſture? 2. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Kneeling be not a Deviation from that Example which our Lord ſet us at the firſt Inſtitution? 3. Whether Kneeling be not unſuitable and Repugnant to the Nature of the Lord's Supper, as being no Table Geſture? The firſt Part.</p>
            <p>Conſiderations of preſent uſe, conſidering the Danger Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting from the Change of our Church-Government.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Perſwaſive to Communion with the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A Reſolution of ſome Caſes of Conſcience, which Reſpect Church-Communion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Caſe of indifferent things, uſed in the Worſhip of God, Propoſed and Stated by conſidering theſe Queſtions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. A Diſcourſe about Edification.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Reſolution of this Caſe of Conſcience, <hi>Whether the Church of</hi> England'<hi>s Symbolizing ſo far as it doth with the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>makes it unlawful to hold Communion with the Church of</hi> England?</p>
            <p n="6">6. A Letter to <hi>Anonymus,</hi> in Anſwer to his Three Letters to Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> about Church-Communion.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Certain Caſes of Conſcience reſolved, concerning the Lawfulneſs of Joyning with Forms of Prayer in Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. The firſt Part.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The Caſe of Mixt Communion. Whether it be lawful to Separate from a Church upon the account of promiſcuous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations and Mixt Communions?</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
